<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Biosystems Engineering Blog</title><link>https://kkremitzki.github.io/</link><description>Notes on my journey in biosystems engineering.</description><atom:link href="/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2018 10:04:08 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Google Summer of Code 2018 with FreeCAD</title><link>/blog/google-summer-of-code-2018-with-freecad/</link><dc:creator>Kurt Kremitzki</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hello all! This post is my final work product for GSoC 2018 for the FreeCAD project.
The main center for communication for FreeCAD is the forums, but we also coordinated things
through the #freecad channel on Freenode.
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://forum.freecadweb.org/viewtopic.php?f=8&amp;amp;t=28478"&gt;The main thread for my project was here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarize my project: FreeCAD is a complex application with an extensive dependency tree. The packaging
situation has always trailed the tip of development, which means users don't get to see the best FreeCAD
has to offer, and people trying to help new users have to deal with sometimes years-old bugs.
The goal was to improve the general ecosystem of the FreeCAD stack, and to cut down on technical debt to
make things easier moving forward. After some consideration it was decided to focus on Debian packaging
since that would be the most 'ecologically good'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I began with a rough knowledge of Debian packaging, but now feel competent
enough to want to take over the maintenance of Debian packaging for FreeCAD and several other packages
within the Debian Science Team, which will improve the free software engineering experience in Debian
as well as its derivatives such as Ubuntu and Linux Mint. In fact, I plan on trying to offically become
a Debian Maintainer and then Debian Developer. On the 4th of July during the middle of the project
I drove to Houston for a GPG keysigning, so the wheels are already in motion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post will summarize my work throughout the summer chronologically, mostly linking to emails in
the Debian Science mailing list, pull requests on Debian's Gitlab instance or Github, and to some repositories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More detailed information can be found at &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://salsa.debian.org/users/kkremitzki-guest"&gt;https://salsa.debian.org/users/kkremitzki-guest&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="coding-period-0-community-bonding-period-april-23-may-14"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Coding Period 0, Community Bonding Period (April 23 - May 14)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;May 8: RFS for python-fluids: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/05/msg00044.html"&gt;https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/05/msg00044.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Packaging this was part of learning more about Debian packaging, and because I'm a fan of the library
for its use in fluids engineering - part of overall ecosystem improvements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="coding-period-1-may-14-june-15"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Coding Period 1 (May 14 - June 15)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most of the first coding period was spent working on FreeCAD 0.17 packaging, as well as packaging Netgen 6.2.1804
and updating Gmsh to use OCCT, which I packaged prior to GSoC. I didn't finish them quite in time for submission
within the first coding period. I also spent time working on packaging PySide 2, which is a dependency for
FreeCAD's transition to Qt 5 &amp;amp; Python 3, but backed away after finding it was being worked on by others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;May 17: Netgen PR (Remove unnecessary backup files): &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/NGSolve/netgen/pull/15"&gt;https://github.com/NGSolve/netgen/pull/15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preparation work for packaging Netgen, which is used as a mesher by FreeCAD.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;May 25: Discussion of Netgen 6.2.1804 work: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/05/msg00101.html"&gt;https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/05/msg00101.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This was just me announcing that I was working on this so as to help not duplicate work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="coding-period-2-june-15-july-13"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Coding Period 2 (June 15 - July 13)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;June 19: Improvements to fluids after suggestions: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/06/msg00031.html"&gt;https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/06/msg00031.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;June 20: OpenFOAM 5 experimentation announced: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/06/msg00038.html"&gt;https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/06/msg00038.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This package is part of the FreeCAD ecosystem by way of its CFD (Computational Fluid Dynamics) workbench.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;June 21: RFS for netgen: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/06/msg00039.html"&gt;https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/06/msg00039.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Note: RFS = request for sponsorship, i.e. a submission of packaging work for Debian project members.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;June 21: RFS for gmsh: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/06/msg00040.html"&gt;https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/06/msg00040.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gmsh is another mesher used by FreeCAD.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;June 21: RFS for freecad: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/06/msg00041.html"&gt;https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/06/msg00041.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This was the packaging work for the FreeCAD 0.17 release.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;June 21: RFS for if97: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/06/msg00042.html"&gt;https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/06/msg00042.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This was another ecosystem project I worked on, a dependency for CoolProp, a powerful thermodynamics library.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;July 8: FreeCAD PR (Detect OCCT at new Debian location): &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/1545"&gt;https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/1545&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This was a housekeeping PR as a result of my Debian packaging work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;July 8: FreeCAD-Doc initial commit: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD-Doc/commits/master"&gt;https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD-Doc/commits/master&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The freecad-doc package was removed from Debian in 2016 for Debian Free Software Guidelines reasons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;July 11: Updated PPA to OCCT 7.3: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://launchpad.net/~freecad-maintainers/+archive/ubuntu/freecad-daily/+packages"&gt;https://launchpad.net/~freecad-maintainers/+archive/ubuntu/freecad-daily/+packages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This was a backport of Debian packaging work for OCCT 7.3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="coding-period-3-july-13-aug-14"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Coding Period 3 (July 13 - Aug 14)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;July 26: PR for horizon-eda (Support build against OCCT): &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/carrotIndustries/horizon/pull/181/files"&gt;https://github.com/carrotIndustries/horizon/pull/181/files&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As part of packaging OCCT, it is planned to phase out OCE (a community fork of OCCT which has stalled in development) and this
was more housekeeping work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;July 27: PR for deal.ii (Update dependencies &amp;amp; rules for liboce-&amp;gt;libocct transition): &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://salsa.debian.org/science-team/deal.ii/merge_requests/1"&gt;https://salsa.debian.org/science-team/deal.ii/merge_requests/1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Similar as above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;July 29: RFS for ulmo: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/07/msg00042.html"&gt;https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/07/msg00042.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This was an ecosystem packaging work, as this library was very useful for me in hydrology and for various agricultural engineering data needs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Aug 7: RFS for openfoam: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/08/msg00011.html"&gt;https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/08/msg00011.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My submission for OpenFOAM 5 was delayed by the release of OpenFOAM 6.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Aug 8: RFS for openvoronoi: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/08/msg00022.html"&gt;https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/08/msg00022.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This was a new dependency for FreeCAD's Path workbench which was relicensed so it could be directly integrated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Aug 8: RFS for opencamlib: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/08/msg00023.html"&gt;https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/08/msg00023.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Similar as above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Aug 10: PR for smesh (Fix GCC8 FTBFS): &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/LaughlinResearch/SMESH/pull/9"&gt;https://github.com/LaughlinResearch/SMESH/pull/9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part of packaging work for SMESH, a mesher used by FreeCAD which is included in the FreeCAD source (which is generally undesirable, and so packaging it would allow us to remove the included copy.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Aug 12: RFS for pivy: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/08/msg00041.html"&gt;https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/08/msg00041.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PySide 2 was a dependency for pivy, so once it was packaged I was able to submit my work for pivy, which required upstreaming Python 3 support from FreeCAD's fork. This package was the last dependency for FreeCAD's Qt 5 &amp;amp; Python 3 transition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Aug 14: RFS for freecad-doc: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=906105"&gt;https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=906105&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Packaging for freecad-doc was delayed by my desire, by way of providing a multi-language supported package, to say thanks to the FreeCAD community translators who provided thorough French and Italian translations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Aug 14: SMESH repo: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://salsa.debian.org/kkremitzki-guest/salome-smesh"&gt;https://salsa.debian.org/kkremitzki-guest/salome-smesh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Packaging external SMESH is incomplete, as its current CMake instructions don't append the library version to the shared library, which will require patching.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Aug 14: CoolProp repo: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://salsa.debian.org/kkremitzki-guest/coolprop"&gt;https://salsa.debian.org/kkremitzki-guest/coolprop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Similar as above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that GSoC is done I am excited to continue working within the Debian Science Team. Besides an upcoming FreeCAD 0.18 release,
I have several packages I plan to make improvements to and to package for Debian, and ultimately to integrate into future
FreeCAD workbenches as part of my plan to make it the ultimate 3D engineering toolbox!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I must say thanks to the FreeCAD and Debian communities for working with me, and to my GSoC mentors and GSoC itself
for providing me this wonderful opportunity. May it continue providing valuable opportunities for others for many years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>/blog/google-summer-of-code-2018-with-freecad/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2018 08:51:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Looking Back on 2017</title><link>/blog/looking-back-on-2017/</link><dc:creator>Kurt Kremitzki</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;2017 has been an incredible year for me with lots of opportunities, but many
challenges as well. In the spring, I got a (lab) teaching opportunity for a
50-student Measurement &amp;amp; Control of Biological Systems course, culminating in
17 teams making maze-solving autonomous robots. There's a higher level of
mastery to be attained by teaching others, and in that regard, it was an
incredible experience. Teaching, however, is well outside my comfort zone, and
in that regard it had some difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the summer, I was able to work on a Google Summer of Code project/pseudo-internship.
Working in a mix of Python and C++ was again an interesting challenge since
I'm much more familiar with the former than the latter, and even my experience
with other languages lies on the Python side of the interpreted/compiled,
dynamic/static typing divide. Still, it was an invaluable experience since C++
rules the domain of finite element analysis and computational fluid dynamics,
which I want to explore further. Particularly, FreeCAD is the perfect vehicle for
engineering computer modeling, so I have high hopes for my future with the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the summer, I passed the exam for the Linux Foundation Certified
System Administrator. This was an opportunity provided by a scholarship given
in part because of my work using Python to analyze the efficiency of backyard
irrigation systems in the Yucatán back in early 2016, so it was great to finally
see the culmination of that work. As a little celebration project, I decided to
begin running my own Linux mail server, which has been a great success. There
were a few hiccups with blacklists on Yahoo and Outlook, but I was ultimately
able to get it working with all the major email providers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also embarked on a project I've been wanting to do for a long time: running
my own Linux router. I found a great series of tutorials on setting up such a
router using Ubuntu and the Pine64 board, and have had excellent results since.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also been spending time here and there researching a really promising
project, FreeIPA. It's a sort of competitor to Active Directory in the identity
management space, mostly made up of a combination of an LDAP, Kerberos, and
certificate server. I'm running a sort of pseudo-small business in my home
network using my FreeIPA server as a centralized authentication, authorization,
and identity server, and it's been a great experience so far; I hope to apply it
in reality with the FreeCAD project one day. Look out for future posts on the
topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the fall, I began my final year at Texas A&amp;amp;M. My capstone project and team
was assigned. Our project involves analyzing the flood resiliency of the Houston
area and proposing an ecological engineering design to improve that resiliency and
mitigate the effects of future extreme flood events such as was seen during
Hurricane Harvey. We are using an open-source toolchain involving PostGIS, Python,
and QGIS, and the project is really quite exciting since our analysis could be applied
to other coastal cities and regions facing extreme weather events in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Altogether, it's been a great year, but I foresee 2018 being even better. If
you're reading this, I want to wish you a happy new year with hope for the same!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>/blog/looking-back-on-2017/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2017 07:30:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>GSoC Week 12: Final Work Product</title><link>/blog/gsoc-week-12-final-work-product/</link><dc:creator>Kurt Kremitzki</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Well, it's time to finally wrap up the summer!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's been a really great and rewarding opportunity, so I first want to thank everyone at Google and beyond who helped put GSoC together,
as well as my mentor Stefan Tröger for providing feedback and guidance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was able to work with code that ranged almost the entire stack of FreeCAD dependencies: from low-level OpenCASCADE code involving
quaternions &amp;amp; transformations, geometry &amp;amp; topology; to the scene graph library Coin3D we have to thank for our pretty screenshots;
the connection between C++ and Python code, which I have a feeling will be useful later in my engineering career; and all the way up to the
Qt GUI in both C++ as well as its Python interface PySide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, I feel very prepared to continue working with the FreeCAD project and look forward to doing so. I really think it's a great
program and hope to use it for many years in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So again, my thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main goal of the project was to get test coverage of the Part Design Workbench, and to explore it to find showstopping bugs. The only
remaining one involves a crash in ShapeBinder, discussed at &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://freecadweb.org/tracker/view.php?id=2517"&gt;https://freecadweb.org/tracker/view.php?id=2517&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I fixed quite a few bugs and I think the general experience with the workbench is better.
Test coverage is there for all the tools, and I'd say the workbench is ready for the public, so now the major work is to release FreeCAD 0.17,
the biggest FreeCAD release ever, with its new Part Design (no longer "NEXT") Workbench.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My other goal of improvements to Boolean Operation was made unnecessary by someone else's PR in May.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last goal, improvements to the Attachment Editor, ended up being a little too big for this GSoC, and could even possibly serve
as a good GSoC project for next summer, although whoever does it had better be fairly artistic at making explanatory yet small icons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, I'd say the summer was a success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Altogether, my code contribution can be summarized with 7 PRs and one experimental branch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PR's:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/816"&gt;https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/816&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/829"&gt;https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/829&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/848"&gt;https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/848&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/869"&gt;https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/869&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/899"&gt;https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/899&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/920"&gt;https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/920&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/957"&gt;https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/957&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experimental Attachment Editor/PartDesign Datum Tools branch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/kkremitzki/freecad/tree/pdn_datum_tools"&gt;https://github.com/kkremitzki/freecad/tree/pdn_datum_tools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's my summary posts, summarized:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/blog/gsoc-week-1-recap/"&gt;/blog/gsoc-week-1-recap/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/blog/gsoc-week-2-recap/"&gt;/blog/gsoc-week-2-recap/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/blog/gsoc-week-3-recap/"&gt;/blog/gsoc-week-3-recap/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/blog/gsoc-week-4-recap/"&gt;/blog/gsoc-week-4-recap/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/blog/gsoc-week-5-recap/"&gt;/blog/gsoc-week-5-recap/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/blog/gsoc-week-6-recap/"&gt;/blog/gsoc-week-6-recap/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/blog/gsoc-week-7-recap/"&gt;/blog/gsoc-week-7-recap/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/blog/gsoc-week-8-recap/"&gt;/blog/gsoc-week-8-recap/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/blog/gsoc-week-9-recap/"&gt;/blog/gsoc-week-9-recap/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/blog/gsoc-week-10-recap/"&gt;/blog/gsoc-week-10-recap/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/blog/gsoc-week-11-recap/"&gt;/blog/gsoc-week-11-recap/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>/blog/gsoc-week-12-final-work-product/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 27 Aug 2017 17:50:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>GSoC Week 11 Recap</title><link>/blog/gsoc-week-11-recap/</link><dc:creator>Kurt Kremitzki</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, it looks like solid, usable improvements to the Attachment Editor are unlikely to be ready for a PR
by the end of my GSoC, although I will publish my experimental branch which uses Python for the datum tools and uses the Python-based
Attachment Editor I mentioned previously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, as a consolation I did finalize some additional tests for PartDesign Hole, so my goal of functional coverage of the PartDesign tools
succeeded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I think with this foray into GUI code, I've hit nearly the full stack of libraries used in FreeCAD this summer. It feels pretty nice, because
I feel prepared to tackle whatever problem I want to in the FreeCAD project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>/blog/gsoc-week-11-recap/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 22 Aug 2017 12:31:55 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>GSoC Week 10 Recap</title><link>/blog/gsoc-week-10-recap/</link><dc:creator>Kurt Kremitzki</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final portion of GSoC for me will be dedicated to working on improvements to the Attachment Editor, and this post will essentially be my design
for what those improvements will look like. The Attachment Editor is available in the Part Workbench through Python. One can for example create a simple
Part Cube, select it, then click Part -&amp;gt; Attachment. It also is used when creating datum geometry in Part Design, or when creating a primitive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few screenshots:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure align-center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="command palette" src="/images/gsoc-10-1.png"&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 1. The Python-based Attachment Editor in the Part workbench.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure align-center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="command palette" src="/images/gsoc-10-2.png"&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 2. Creating a Datum Plane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating datum geometry is a key part of the Part Design process, so it's helpful for it to be very easy and intuitive. The current
Attachment Mode information especially can be quite overwhelming to a beginner, however. Especially considering how improvements
to the Attachment Editor could be reused in a future Assembly Workbench, it was decided to look into improving these tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first, most obvious improvement here would be inactivating the "Extra placement" section when inactive. This could
possibly be accomplished by making a separate collapsible section which automatically hides when there is no attachment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second, and tougher improvement, involves reworking the current the four attachment selections and the attachment mode.
Reference names probably don't need to be more than 3/4ths the width of the page. The methods for selecting references via
an activation button, and deleting via clearing out the text are not user-friendly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The four-reference list here would ideally be replaced with an icon-based grid, which starts out empty. Each selection's icon would
be based on its type, e.g. Vertex, Edge, Face, Curve, etc., where available, and a generic icon for unrecognized types. The selection's name
could be displayed in a shortened form, e.g. "MyLongShapeNameIs...". This approach could be extended for future Assembly use by adding a scrollbar
on the icons, allowing for several rows of attachment references, 4 at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tool could be very user-friendly, as invalid reference icons can be highlighted red, and when the attachment is complete, the reference set's icons
can be highlighted green. Ghosted icons can be displayed as needed for a selected Attachment Mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A similar approach for Attachment Mode could be used. Using a 4-icon row with a scrollbar, attachment modes can be explained with a short label and
an icon, where feasible; hopefully the large size will allow for expressive icons. When a mode is moused over or selected, the remaining references required
can be displayed in the reference selection area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Altogether, (i) splitting out the placement and toggling when it has no effect (i.e. there is no attachment) and (ii) reworking Reference Selection and Attachment Mode
dialogs to use unified icon list GUI code, as well as (iii) making the icon set to explain the attachment concepts to users, comprise the components of this
"Attachment Editor Improvement" project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>/blog/gsoc-week-10-recap/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 20 Aug 2017 12:22:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>GSoC Week 9 Recap</title><link>/blog/gsoc-week-9-recap/</link><dc:creator>Kurt Kremitzki</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I celebrated my birthday in south Texas last week! I was about 3 miles from the future SpaceX launch facility opening in 2018.
It'll be great to possibly see launches to Mars from there in the next few years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mostly spent this week working on the bugs I mentioned last week. I wanted to try to make a dent in the outstanding bugs I've found.
Unfortunately, my lack of C++ background (compared to Python) really hampered this; it's a little bit like trying to run before you walk.
In the end, I only fixed the Revolution bug(s). In the case where a revolution is attempted on the same plane as the sketch, resulting in e.g. a flat disc,
the issue was that the code was checking the angle between the sketch's normal and the revolution plane's normal, looking for a 0° angle. However,
it was failing to fail in the case of a 180° angle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also added a simple convenience check for all tools in Part Design: if you open a document with only one body and try to click a PDN tool's button,
the single body will be auto-activated instead of popping up a warning. If there are no bodies or more than one, the warning still occurs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>/blog/gsoc-week-9-recap/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2017 02:18:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>GSoC Week 8 Recap</title><link>/blog/gsoc-week-8-recap/</link><dc:creator>Kurt Kremitzki</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Total tool coverage lasted less than a week! It's a good thing though, because that means a new tool &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/898"&gt;landed in master&lt;/a&gt;: PartDesign Hole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object class="align-center" data="/images/PartDesign_Hole.svg" type="image/svg+xml"&gt;
Part Design Hole tool&lt;/object&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a really great tool for the Part Design WB not only because holes (and their corresponding fasteners) are ubiquitous in part design generally,
but also because the tool does a good job of capturing that information into a FreeCAD object that can be later be hooked into for both the
Assembly and TechDraw workbenches. For example, the options I've selected in the following screenshot could be used to complete a technical drawing
for this part in FreeCAD, and that information exchange could be done in an automated and customizable way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Part Design Hole tool" class="align-center" src="/images/gsoc-8-1.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This information could also be used by the Path WB to generate control code for open-source, automated manufacturing processes and machines, so it's really
great to have such a full-featured tool added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent some time trying to find bugs in the tool, but didn't really find any. The only gotcha I noticed is related to the orientation of sketches which serve as the
basis for holes. There is no Reverse option for the Hole feature itself, so for example, if you have a sketch on the "bottom" of an object but not attached to it,
you may need to set the Map Reversed option for the sketch itself to true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some tests will be forthcoming for Hole, but besides that, I also spent some time looking at few outstanding bugs in C++-land.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Particularly,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(mentioned in week 5) ShapeBinder crash when base object not initially selected due to null pointer dereference&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(mentioned in week 3) Revolution has unhandled error for some bad revolution axis choices, does bad revolution without error for others&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(new) Pipe fails when its path is a loop. For example, a Pipe with a circle as a base and a larger, orthogonal circle passing through the base should become a torus.
Currently, it fails with the wonderfully verbose error message 'TopoDS::Shell'.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>/blog/gsoc-week-8-recap/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2017 08:19:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>GSoC Week 7 Recap</title><link>/blog/gsoc-week-7-recap/</link><dc:creator>Kurt Kremitzki</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I hit a nice milestone this week! With &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/899"&gt;PR 899&lt;/a&gt; I hit total tool &lt;em&gt;test&lt;/em&gt; coverage for the Part Design workbench.
Now, what exactly does that mean? Well, if you look at my screenshot of the workbench tools from Week 2, every one of those is now covered by tests with most
key functionality hit. Some of them, like the dressup features Fillet and Chamfer, only have one test, either because the tool is simple or because further tests
lie outside the scope of the Part Design workbench (e.g. testing the topological naming robustness of Fillet to recalculation.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PartDesign Primitive (Box, Cylinder, Sphere, Cone, Ellipsoid, Torus, Prism, and Wedge) tests were interesting to write.
I was able to cover basic construction of both Additive and Subtractive primitives of each type by simply making a large Additive Primitive
and smaller Subtractive Primitive inside the first, and then ensuring that the ensuing Shape's Volume property was about equal to
the difference in volumes according to the formula for that shape, e.g.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\[
\mathrm{Shape.Volume}\ \approx V = \frac{4}{3}\pi (R^3 - r^3)
\]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for Additive-&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(R\)&lt;/span&gt; and Subtractive-&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(r\)&lt;/span&gt; Primitive Spheres.
I had to look up a few volume formulas but otherwise the tests for the lengthly list in the parentheses above went quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also fixed a bug with Loft sections not being hidden, so e.g. the Sketches being lofted to or through were still visible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, there was an issue with both Loft and Pipe not claiming children correctly in the tree which I fixed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>mathjax</category><guid>/blog/gsoc-week-7-recap/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Jul 2017 20:30:58 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>GSoC Week 6 Recap</title><link>/blog/gsoc-week-6-recap/</link><dc:creator>Kurt Kremitzki</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Short post this week! I was in Spokane, Washington, from July 15-19th for a robotics competition being held at the Annual International Meeting of my professional society,
the American Society of Agricultural &amp;amp; Biological Engineers, or ASABE. I only had a smattering of time to work on the various FreeCAD bugs I have mentioned in previous posts
so there isn't much to report on that front. Instead, I'll leave a picture from the beautiful Spokane downtown area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/gsoc-6-1.jpg" class="align-center" src="/images/gsoc-6-1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>/blog/gsoc-week-6-recap/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Jul 2017 05:26:28 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>GSoC Week 5 recap</title><link>/blog/gsoc-week-5-recap/</link><dc:creator>Kurt Kremitzki</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This week started out with some interesting discussions on the future Python structure of FreeCAD, over
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://forum.freecadweb.org/viewtopic.php?f=10&amp;amp;t=23197"&gt;on the forums&lt;/a&gt;. This was especially salient
as I have a bit of pain interacting with parts of the FreeCAD Python API and improvements to it would
be a good long-term goal after finishing GSoC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided that the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;TestPartDesignApp.py&lt;/tt&gt; file I had been working in thus far needed splitting up,
as I was cramming almost every new test into it.
The &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/blob/master/src/Mod/PartDesign/TestPartDesignApp.py"&gt;new version of this file&lt;/a&gt;
is a pretty nice indicator of the overall status of PartDesign test coverage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also added some basic tests for datum tools, covering simple creation scenarios. While exploring the 4th datum
tool, &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;ShapeBinder&lt;/tt&gt;, I found a bug that causes a crash, so I will need to look into that shortly to see if it's an
easy fix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;LinearPattern&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PolarPattern&lt;/tt&gt; got 6 new tests each, covering all the major variations of sketch-
or primitive-based features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I added one new test for each of the dressup features, &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Fillet&lt;/tt&gt;, &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Chamfer&lt;/tt&gt;, &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Draft&lt;/tt&gt;, and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Thickness&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the pull request summarizing my work: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/869"&gt;https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/869&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table border="1" class="docutils"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col width="33%"&gt;
&lt;col width="28%"&gt;
&lt;col width="11%"&gt;
&lt;col width="28%"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead valign="bottom"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th class="head"&gt;tool category&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;initial, current test count&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;status&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;notes&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;datum tools&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0, 3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ready&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;found shapebinder crash bug&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;add. &amp;amp; sub. features/primitives&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15, 15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ready&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;transformations&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3, 15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ready&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;all done but MultiTransform&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;dressup features&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0, 4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ready&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;boolean operation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0, 0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ready&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>freecad</category><category>gsoc</category><guid>/blog/gsoc-week-5-recap/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 11 Jul 2017 19:45:35 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>