<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Biosystems Engineering Blog</title><link>https://kkremitzki.github.io/</link><description>Notes on my journey in biosystems engineering.</description><atom:link href="/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2018 05:20:43 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Free Software Activities in November 2018</title><link>/blog/free-software-activities-in-november-2018/</link><dc:creator>Kurt Kremitzki</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class="section" id="intro"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome to another of my monthly summaries on my work in the free software
world. My mission is to make engineering and science available for everyone,
and Debian, the Universal Operating System, is my weapon of choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I received some feedback on my last post that I made it seem I would be
stepping away from my role maintaining FreeCAD and other packages on the Debian
Science Team, which was an unfortunate miscommunication on my part. Mainly, I
just would like to reduce the proportion of my overall free software time on
it, from its current amount, nearly 100%, to a roughly even 1/3rd split between
Debian Science, FreeCAD, and PostCAD. The latter is a promising personal
project to make an OpenCASCADE-powered CAD extension for PostgreSQL, bringing
support for CAD file formats, datatypes, and algorithms to the powerful
Postgres ecosystem, similar to what PostCAD has done for geospatial analysis.
This could serve as a backend for both FreeCAD in the short term, and in the
long term, it could power a web-based version of FreeCAD, perhaps with some
Django-powered middleware serving a REST API for some WebGL-based frontend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, besides summarizing my work this month, I also plan to give a synopsis on
my Debian packaging, for both what's in-progress and on my wishlist. As you'll
see, it's quite extensive. My hope is that by whittling away at both lists, my
Debian Science work can focus more on maintenance of existing packages, and
free up some time for other things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="sponsors"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Sponsors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My work on Debian Science, FreeCAD, and PostCAD is &lt;cite&gt;supported by my patrons on
Patreon &amp;lt;https://patreon.com/kkremitzki&amp;gt;&lt;/cite&gt;. While I had created a Liberapay a
while back, I never got any traction with it, and I found out recently that it
was because I had not set it up to actually receive payments. So, if you don't
like Patreon for whatever reason, you can also &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://liberapay.com/kkremitzki"&gt;support me on Liberapay&lt;/a&gt;. Just to round things out, if you don't
like either of those platforms, you can also &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://paypal.me/kkremitzki"&gt;help support my work via PayPal&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="transition-for-coin3"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Transition for coin3&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coin3D is a scene graph library and a fundamental part of FreeCAD.
Unfortunately, it hasn't had a release since 2011, but development has been
picking up recently, so it's likely that a release is not too far off. Even
without a formal release, several improvements have been made including CMake
support, so it's time to prepare a transition in advance of the Debian 10
release. Luckily, Leo Palomo-Avellaneda has taken the initiative of getting
this transition started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, the new Coin3D package is available in Debian Experimental as we
prepare the reverse-dependencies to build against it. For FreeCAD, we directly
depend on Pivy, which are Python bindings for Coin. Pivy, in turn, depends on
Coin and SoQt, which is a Qt GUI component toolkit library for Coin. A
pre-release version of SoQt is also being packaged since, like Coin, CMake
support has been added, as well as support for Qt 5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I've been grinding my gears on building Pivy against the new
Coin and SoQt for a good part of this month, which is especially troublesome
since FreeCAD's transition to Python 3 is blocked by the upload of a new Pivy,
which I prepared earlier this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With any luck, I'll be able to help Leo finish the Coin and SoQt transition and
have Pivy prepared in December.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="gmsh-update"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Gmsh Update&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gmsh is a 3D finite element mesh generator with built-in pre- and
post-processing facilities. It's also one of the main meshers used by FreeCAD's
Finite Element Modeling Workbench, besides Netgen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently Debian has Gmsh 3.0.6, but a new major version was released in
August. I've already prepared this new major version for testing in FreeCAD's
Community Extras PPA, but I hadn't cleaned up the packaging yet to submit to
Debian. However, in November, there were two point releases, 4.0.5 and 4.0.6,
so I wasn't able to complete this work this month, but I'm sure it'll be done
in early December.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One major piece of information regarding Gmsh 4 is a change in the API: the
libjava-gmsh3 package in Debian was never meant to be a public API, and so Gmsh
upstream has requested that we no longer ship it. To offset this, there have
been refinements for the actual public API, which officially comes in C, Python
3 and (new) Julia flavors. However, I haven't found much information on Julia
packaging in Debian, so I'll likely hold off on that package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="pyside-2-rebuild-ppa-plans"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;PySide 2 Rebuild &amp;amp; PPA Plans&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since FreeCAD is an LGPL-licensed Qt project, we must use PySide and not PyQt
to do Qt things with Python. Because of this, the FreeCAD migration to Qt 5 on
Debian was blocked by the packaging of PySide 2, which was completed by
Freexian SARL over the summer. In Debian, we now have a Qt 5-enabled FreeCAD,
although our daily builds PPA is still using Qt 4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides the Qt 4-&amp;gt;5 transition, we're also finishing up a Python 2-&amp;gt;3
transition. At the end of the summer I published a &lt;cite&gt;freecad-python3&lt;/cite&gt; package in
the PPA which also used Qt 5. However, it wasn't really fully usable, moreso a
proof-of-concept that such a build indeed buildable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, the Debian FreeCAD package has begun to diverge from the FreeCAD
PPAs; besides Qt 5 builds not being available currently, the Debian package has
also been split into several packages (e.g. &lt;cite&gt;libfreecad&lt;/cite&gt;, &lt;cite&gt;freecad-common&lt;/cite&gt;,
etc. packages) in order to better comply with Debian Policy and the Filesystem
Hierarchy Standard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, there's a bit of work to do to catch the PPAs up. First, the package split
needs to be done. Then, I need to upload an alternative &lt;cite&gt;freecad-daily&lt;/cite&gt; package
for Qt 5 builds, separate from Python 3. Once that is done and has undergone
some testing, &lt;cite&gt;freecad-daily&lt;/cite&gt; can be replaced by it, and it in turn can be
replaced by a &lt;cite&gt;freecad-python3&lt;/cite&gt; package for further testing. Since FreeCAD's
0.18 release is imminent, I'll need to get this taken care of during December,
so stay tuned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="packaging-in-progress"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Packaging in Progress&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first packaging list is all the software I've already started packaging. For
some, it's almost complete, and for others, I've only just begun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of these lists is not to give status updates, but to announce what
all I'm interested in to anyone reading this, and to give an idea of how much
packaging work I have in mind to improve this usage of Debian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="cantera"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;cantera&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="homepage-github"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://cantera.org/"&gt;Homepage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/Cantera/cantera"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Cantera is an open-source suite of tools for problems involving chemical
kinetics, thermodynamics, and transport processes.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had this package working and waiting to be sponsored, but it looks like it currently fails
to build from source, so this just requires some maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="coolprop"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;coolprop&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id1"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.coolprop.org/"&gt;Homepage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/CoolProp/CoolProp"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
CoolProp is a thermophysical property database and wrappers for a selection
of programming environments. It offers similar functionality to REFPROP,
although CoolProp is open-source and free.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This package was previously building completely, but failing when one would attempt to do
an &lt;cite&gt;import coolprop&lt;/cite&gt;. Now that it's been a while since I worked with it, it
seems to be failing to build.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="elmerfem"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;elmerfem&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id2"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.elmerfem.org/"&gt;Homepage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/ElmerCSC/elmerfem"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Elmer is a finite element software for numerical solution of partial
differential equations. Elmer is capable of handling any number of equations
and is therefore ideally suited for the simulation of multiphysical problems.
It includes models, for example, of structural mechanics, fluid dynamics, heat
transfer and electromagnetics. Users can also write their own equations that
can be dynamically linked with the main program.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was previously in Debian but removed due to abandonment, so a great deal
of the work is already done, but it also requires quite a bit of updating to
current Debian standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="if97"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;if97&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="pdf-standard-github"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.iapws.org/relguide/IF97-Rev.pdf"&gt;PDF Standard&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/CoolProp/IF97"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Open-source C++ implementation of the IAPWS-IF97 equations to calculate
properties of the pure water substance.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a dependency of CoolProp, and I already have it packaged and waiting
for sponsorship at &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://salsa.debian.org/science-team/if97"&gt;https://salsa.debian.org/science-team/if97&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="ifcopenshell"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;ifcopenshell&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id3"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ifcopenshell.org/"&gt;Homepage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/IfcOpenShell/IfcOpenShell"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
IfcOpenShell is an open source (LGPL) software library that helps users and
software developers to work with the IFC file format. The IFC file format
can be used to describe building and construction data. The format is
commonly used for Building Information Modelling. IfcOpenShell uses
OpenCASCADE internally to convert the implicit geometry in IFC files into
explicit geometry that any software CAD or modelling package can
understand.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I already have this packaged and awaiting sponsorship at &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://salsa.debian.org/kkremitzki-guest/ifcopenshell"&gt;https://salsa.debian.org/kkremitzki-guest/ifcopenshell&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's also available on the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://launchpad.net/~freecad-community/+archive/ubuntu/ppa"&gt;FreeCAD Community Extras PPA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="ifcplusplus"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;ifcplusplus&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id4"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ifcquery.com/"&gt;Homepage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/ifcquery/ifcplusplus"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
IfcPlusPlus is an open source C++ class model, as well as a reader and
writer for IFC files in STEP format. It features easy and efficient memory
management using smart pointers, a parallel reader for fast parsing on
multi-core CPU's, and a simple IFC viewer application using Qt and
OpenSceneGraph.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I already have this packaged and awaiting sponsorship at &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://salsa.debian.org/kkremitzki-guest/ifcplusplus"&gt;https://salsa.debian.org/kkremitzki-guest/ifcplusplus&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's also available on the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://launchpad.net/~freecad-community/+archive/ubuntu/ppa"&gt;FreeCAD Community Extras PPA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="opencamlib"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;opencamlib&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id6"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.anderswallin.net/tag/opencamlib/"&gt;Homepage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/aewallin/opencamlib"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
OpenCAMLib (OCL) is a C++ library with Python bindings for creating 3D
toolpaths for CNC-machines such as mills and lathes.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I already have this packaged and awaiting sponsorship at &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://salsa.debian.org/science-team/opencamlib"&gt;https://salsa.debian.org/science-team/opencamlib&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's also available on the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://launchpad.net/~freecad-community/+archive/ubuntu/ppa"&gt;FreeCAD Community Extras PPA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="openvoronoi"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;openvoronoi&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id8"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.anderswallin.net/category/cnc/cam/openvoronoi/"&gt;Homepage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/aewallin/openvoronoi"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
2D voronoi diagram for point and line-segment sites using incremental
topology-oriented algorithm. C++ with Python bindings.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I already have this packaged and awaiting sponsorship at &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://salsa.debian.org/kkremitzki-guest/openvoronoi"&gt;https://salsa.debian.org/kkremitzki-guest/openvoronoi&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's also available on the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://launchpad.net/~freecad-community/+archive/ubuntu/ppa"&gt;FreeCAD Community Extras PPA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="projectchrono"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;projectchrono&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id10"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://projectchrono.org/"&gt;Homepage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/projectchrono/chrono"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
C++ library for multi-physics simulation. The applications areas in which
Chrono is most often used are vehicle dynamics, robotics, and machine
design. In vehicle dynamics, Chrono has mature support for tire/terrain
interaction modeling and simulation.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've only roughly begun packaging this, and I'm already tired of typing
&lt;cite&gt;libprojectchrono&lt;/cite&gt;. Anyway, it's a rather large set of components which will be
broken up into several packages. Luckily, things are done in a pretty normal
way so I don't imagine this will be difficult to finish packaging, just a
little time-costly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="smesh"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;smesh&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="github"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/LaughlinResearch/smesh"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
A stand-alone library of the mesh framework from the Salome Platform&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've gotten this standalone version of SMESH packaged and awaiting sponsorship
at &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://salsa.debian.org/kkremitzki-guest/salome-smesh"&gt;https://salsa.debian.org/kkremitzki-guest/salome-smesh&lt;/a&gt;.  Eventually, I want
to package the entire Salome Platform, but it's extremely large and really
several source packages. Packaging this as an intermediate step allows us to
remove SMESH from FreeCAD's included sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's also available on the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://launchpad.net/~freecad-community/+archive/ubuntu/ppa"&gt;FreeCAD Community Extras PPA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="xcfem"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;xcfem&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id12"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://sites.google.com/site/xcfemanalysis/"&gt;Homepage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/xcfem/xc"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
XC is an open source FEA program designed to solve structural analysis
problems.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This library is supposed to be an alternative to the not-quite-freely licensed
OpenSees, which is used in seismic research and analysis. There has been some
interest in the FreeCAD forums about using this, so I'm beginning packaging it
in advance. However, it seems a bit complicated as it requires multiple
sources, the GitHub &lt;cite&gt;xcfem/xc&lt;/cite&gt; repo as well as &lt;cite&gt;xcfem/xc_utils&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="wishlist-packages"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Wishlist Packages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="geom"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2geom&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="homepage-gitlab"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://lib2geom.sourceforge.net/"&gt;Homepage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://gitlab.com/inkscape/lib2geom"&gt;GitLab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
lib2geom (2Geom in private life) was initially a library developed for
Inkscape but will provide a robust computational geometry framework for any
application. It is not a rendering library, instead concentrating on high
level algorithms such as computing arc length.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I looked at this package and it seemed like it will be straightforward to
package, and with the parent project's popularity, someone else may get to it
first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="bimserver"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;bimserver&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id13"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/blog/free-software-activities-in-november-2018/bimserver.org"&gt;Homepage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/opensourceBIM/BIMserver"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The Building Information Model server (short: BIMserver) enables you to
store and manage the information of a construction (or other building
related) project. Data is stored in the open standard IFC. The BIMserver is
not a fileserver, but it uses a model-driven architecture approach. This
means that IFC data is stored in an underlying database. The main advantage
of this approach is the ability to query, merge and filter the BIM-model
and generate IFC files on the fly.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The integration of BIM with FreeCAD is a very promising endeavor, and letting
FreeCAD be the client in a client-server model provides many potential
benefits. (This is the reason I'm working on PostCAD.) Packaging BIMserver
is a natural decision, then. However, it's a Java application, which I have
little experience with language-wise and none in terms of packaging it in
Debian, so this one has a bit of a difficulty associated with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="cadquery"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;cadquery&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id14"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://dcowden.github.io/cadquery/index.html"&gt;Homepage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/dcowden/cadquery"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
CadQuery is an intuitive, easy-to-use python based language for building
parametric 3D CAD models. CadQuery is for 3D CAD what jQuery is for
javascript. Imagine selecting Faces of a 3d object the same way you select
DOM objects with JQuery!&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CadQuery is an interesting project which actually makes use of FreeCAD, and
indeed FreeCAD even has a CadQuery Workbench. This would be nice to package as
a way of extending the FreeCAD ecosystem on Debian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, CadQuery 2 is planning on moving away from FreeCAD to PythonOCC,
which is based on the now behind-the-times OpenCASCADE Community Edition fork,
based on OpenCASCADE 6.9.1; FreeCAD and other projects are moving back to the
mainline OpenCASCADE Technology project which is about to release version
7.4.0. It would be nice if both CadQuery and FreeCAD could instead move to use
PyOCCT as a middle-layer between itself and OpenCASCADE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="libreoffice-code-highlighter"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;libreoffice-code-highlighter&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id15"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://extensions.libreoffice.org/extensions/code-highlighter"&gt;Homepage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/slgobinath/libreoffice-code-highlighter"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
This extension highlights the code snippets for over 350 languages in
LibreOffice.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have packaged a LibreOffice extension before, and it was fairly easy, so I expect this one will be too. However its priority is rather low.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="lib3mf"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;lib3mf&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id16"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://3mf.io/"&gt;Homepage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/3MFConsortium/lib3mf"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Lib3MF is a C++ implementation of the 3D Manufacturing Format file standard.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This seems like a straightforward library to package, but there is no pressing need as FreeCAD does not support it yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="muesli"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;muesli&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="homepage-bitbucket"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://materials.imdea.org/research/simulation-tools/muesli/"&gt;Homepage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bitbucket.org/ignromero/muesli"&gt;BitBucket&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
MUESLI, a Material UnivErSal LIbrary, is a collection of C++ classes and
functions designed to model material behavior at the continuum level.
Developed at IMDEA Materials, it is available to the material science and
computational mechanics community as a suite of standard models and as a
platform for developing new ones.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This seems like a great candidate package for Debian Science but I have had
some difficulty building it, which I need to conquer before packaging can
begin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="cling"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;cling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id17"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://root.cern.ch/cling"&gt;Homepage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/root-project/cling"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Cling is an interactive C++ interpreter, built on top of Clang and LLVM
compiler infrastructure. Cling realizes the read-eval-print loop (REPL)
concept, in order to leverage rapid application development. Implemented as
a small extension to LLVM and Clang, the interpreter reuses their strengths
such as the praised concise and expressive compiler diagnostics.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;cling is an incredible project which should have been packaged already.
Hopefully someone else gets to it first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="dpkg-licenses"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;dpkg-licenses&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id18"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/daald/dpkg-licenses"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
A command line tool which lists the licenses of all installed packages in a Debian-based system (like Ubuntu)&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a small script which gives a summary of the licenses used by the installed packages on your system--a good way to audit packages, e.g. forbidding AGPL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="landlab"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;landlab&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id19"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://landlab.github.io/#/#install"&gt;Homepage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/landlab/landlab"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Landlab is a Python-based modeling environment that allows scientists and
students to build numerical landscape models. Designed for disciplines
that quantify earth surface dynamics such as geomorphology, hydrology,
glaciology, and stratigraphy, it can also be used in related fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Landlab provides components to compute flows (such as water, sediment,
glacial ice, volcanic material, or landslide debris) across a gridded
terrain. With its robust, reusable components, Landlab allows scientists
to quickly build landscape model experiments and compute mass balance
across scales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Landlab is another interesting Debian Science candidate but I have no pressing need to package it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="nikola"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;nikola&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id20"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://getnikola.com/"&gt;Homepage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/getnikola/nikola"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
A static website and blog generator, written in Python.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nikola is what I use to create this blog, but it's somewhat fast moving and a
slow maintainer in Debian previously caused problems, so I don't want to pick
this up until I've leveled up my package maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="osifont"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;osifont&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id21"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fontlibrary.org/en/font/osifont"&gt;Homepage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/hikikomori82/osifont"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
In some European countries, CAD projects must have font which conform to
IS0 3O98 specification. Commercial CADs has this font, but free CADs not.
There is no available free font yet, so this project will fix this. This
font will be created completely from the scratch. Font is created with free
tools like FontForge, Inkscape, Gimp. Font is available under 3 licences:
GNU GPL licence version 3 with GPL font exception, GNU GPL licence version
2 with GPL font exception, GNU LGPL licence version 3 with GPL font
exception.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a bundled font with FreeCAD, so I'd like to separate into its own
package. However, the need to package it is not pressing, so I haven't picked
it up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="pigpio"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;pigpio&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id22"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://abyz.me.uk/rpi/pigpio/"&gt;Homepage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/joan2937/pigpio"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
pigpio is a C library for the Raspberry which allows control of the General
Purpose Input Outputs (GPIO).&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an important tool for teaching with Raspberry Pi's and should be
packaged as soon as possible, I've just had more pressing concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="piscope"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;piscope&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id23"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://abyz.me.uk/rpi/pigpio/piscope.html"&gt;Homepage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/joan2937/piscope"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
A logic analyser (digital waveform viewer).  piscope uses the services of
the pigpio library. pigpio needs to be running on the Pi whose gpios are to
be monitored.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being able to see the waveform of a GPIO pin on a Raspberry Pi is incredibly
useful for teaching robotics and electrical engineering classes with them. This
also needs to be packaged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="pyocct"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;pyocct&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id24"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/LaughlinResearch/pyOCCT"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The pyOCCT project provides Python bindings to the OpenCASCADE 7.2.0
geometry kernel and SMESH 8.3.0 meshing library via pybind11. Together,
this technology stack enables rapid CAD/CAE application development in the
popular Python programming language.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a very promising library for Python OpenCASCADE development, so I'd
like to get it packaged, but it's blocked by getting SMESH packaged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="pyray"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;pyray&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id25"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/ryu577/pyray"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
A 3D rendering library written completely in Python.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A promising library for integrating raytracing functionality directly into
FreeCAD, and for general raytracing in Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="quarter"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;quarter&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="bitbucket"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bitbucket.org/Coin3D/quarter"&gt;BitBucket&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Quarter is a light-weight glue library that provides seamless integration
between the Coin high-level 3D visualization library and Qt's 2D user
interface library.  The functionality in Quarter revolves around
QuarterWidget, a subclass of QGLWidget. This widget provides functionality
for rendering of Coin scenegraphs and translation of QEvents into SoEvents.
Using this widget is as easy as using any other QWidget.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FreeCAD already uses an included (and slightly modified) copy of Quarter in its
source, so I'd like to package Quarter in a standalone fashion as part of
moving FreeCAD away from bundled copies in its source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="rebound"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;rebound&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id26"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://rebound.readthedocs.io/en/latest/"&gt;Homepage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/hannorein/rebound"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
REBOUND is an N-body integrator, i.e. a software package that can integrate
the motion of particles under the influence of gravity. The particles can
represent stars, planets, moons, ring or dust particles. REBOUND is very
flexible and can be customized to accurately and efficiently solve many
problems in astrophysics.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This seems like a really great library to have in Debian Science, but it's not a priority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="sqlint"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;sqlint&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id27"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/purcell/sqlint"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SQLint is a simple command-line linter which reads your SQL files and
reports any syntax errors or warnings it finds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this stage, SQLint checks SQL against the ANSI syntax, and uses the
PostgreSQL SQL parser to achieve this. In time, we hope to add support for
non-standard SQL variants (e.g. MySQL). Contributions are welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This would be a very useful utility to have in Debian, but I always write SQL without flaw the first try. (wink)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="swatmodel"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;swatmodel&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id28"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://swat.tamu.edu/"&gt;Homepage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/WatershedModels/SWAT"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The Soil &amp;amp; Water Assessment Tool is a small watershed to river basin-scale
model used to simulate the quality and quantity of surface and ground water
and predict the environmental impact of land use, land management
practices, and climate change. SWAT is widely used in assessing soil
erosion prevention and control, non-point source pollution control and
regional management in watersheds.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SWAT is a powerful research tool in agricultural engineering, among several
others I'm interested in eventually packaging for Debian. The planned package
will be based on a CMake-enabled fork of the upstream source, which is built
with Intel's Fortran compiler by default and also had to be adapted for
gfortran.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="wger"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;wger&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id29"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://wger.de/en/software/features"&gt;Homepage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/wger-project/wger"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Self hosted FLOSS fitness/workout and weight tracker written with Django&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a very promising application which could be used as both a fitness
tracker as well as a weight/nutrition tracker, something along the lines of a
self-hosted MyFitnessPal. However, my other packaging priorities outweigh this
at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, there you have it! My mostly complete list of in-progress and wishlist
items for Debian packaging. If you have any feedback on packages on the list,
or want to get in touch with me, you can find me &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/thekurtwk"&gt;on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; or send me an email at kurt at kwk.systems.
I'll also be starting to stream my Debian &amp;amp; FreeCAD work very soon, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitch.tv/kkremitzki"&gt;subscribe
to me on Twitch&lt;/a&gt; to get notified when I go
live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>debian freecad postcad</category><guid>/blog/free-software-activities-in-november-2018/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2018 05:20:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Free Software Activities in October 2018</title><link>/blog/free-software-activities-in-october-2018/</link><dc:creator>Kurt Kremitzki</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class="section" id="intro"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome to another monthly summary of my free software work. Currently I'm focusing
on improving the state of packaging for FreeCAD and its ecosystem of dependencies
and related packages in Debian Science. Additionally, I recently revived the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://launchpad.net/~freecad-community/+archive/ubuntu/ppa"&gt;FreeCAD
Community Extras PPA&lt;/a&gt;
as a way of staging these packages out to users for testing. If
you are a FreeCAD user, developer, or simply a user of one of these packages, I would
greatly appreciate your feedback and testing to identify bugs while my packages wait
to make it into the Debian archive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, in the long-term, I plan to move away from spending so much time on Debian
packaging and returning to FreeCAD core development, and a special not-so-secret related project:
PostCAD, providing OpenCASCADE geometry &amp;amp; topology bindings plus CAD data and filetype format support for PostgreSQL, a la PostGIS.
The goal is to build this out as a rich backend which FreeCAD can talk to about neat CAD stuff.
It's a heaping of work, though, so I don't expect to have a public release until mid or late 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to find others who
are interested in contributing to FreeCAD ecosystem packaging for mentorship. That way,
my efforts are maintained by the community and the quality and availability of packages
won't wane with my attention on them. Since FreeCAD participates in Google Summer of
Code, this would be a great opportunity for interested university students to learn
Debian packaging and improve the state of science &amp;amp; engineering software on Debian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, on to my summary!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="debian-news"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Debian News&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This month, I officially became a Debian Maintainer. This is a basic level of formal
membership in the Debian project, and it comes with limited upload rights to the
archive. I can only upload packages for which I am marked as a maintainer, for example
FreeCAD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took advantage of this to upload some improvements for FreeCAD which I had
been sitting on. After a few tweaks, the package was ready for an upgraded upload
from Experimental to Unstable, which begins the process of candidacy for Testing,
the release pocket for the upcoming Debian 10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="debian-freecad-gets-qt-5"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Debian FreeCAD Gets Qt 5&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/freecad-qt5.png" class="align-center" src="/images/freecad-qt5.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most important about this upload, though was that FreeCAD is finally being built
with Qt 5 support. While Qt 5 had been working for quite a while, we were waiting
on a dependency to be uploaded to Debian, PySide 2, which finally was uploaded this
summer. Because this is a big switch to flip, any testing and reporting of bugs for
this Debian package would be appreciated!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="freecad-package-structure-reorganization"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;FreeCAD Package Structure Reorganization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the other major packaging changes for FreeCAD 0.17 is that the package is
no longer a single, monolithic &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;freecad&lt;/tt&gt; package. We now have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;freecad&lt;/tt&gt; metapackage, which installs the other packages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;common files and resources (e.g. images) in &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;freecad-common&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;freecad-runtime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; contains Python 2/3 compatible runtime files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the executable built against Python 2, &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;freecad-python2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and the library files used by the executable, &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;libfreecad-python2-0.17&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several advantages to this approach. The first is that since &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;freecad-common&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;
and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;freecad-runtime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; are just pictures, Python scripts, and the like, we can save
space in the archive by only needing one copy of the package, instead of one for each
supported architecture. For &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;freecad-python2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;libfreecad-python2-0.17&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;, one can
see the advantage in the name: since these are Python 2 specific, we will soon be
able to provide their Python 3 counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideally, by the time of the Debian 10 release, the FreeCAD 0.17 package will provide
both Python 2 and 3 supported versions, and which one you want to use can be switched
between using the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;alternatives&lt;/tt&gt; system, which I will explain later in this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="freecad-python-3-imminent"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;FreeCAD Python 3 Imminent&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like Qt 5, FreeCAD has supported Python 3 for quite some time. (Workbenches and
3rd party code are another story.) However, in Debian, a Python 3-enabled FreeCAD
package is blocked by the pending upload of pivy 0.6. I helped coordinate the upstream
release of this package but due to issues with its dependency Coin3D the upload is stalled
until those issues are resolved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="community-extras-ppa-early-packge-previews"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Community Extras PPA - Early Packge Previews&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we have the Community Extras PPA, it serves as a convenient location for me to upload packages
as soon as I have one completed and ready for testing. Here are my uploads this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="gmsh-4"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Gmsh 4&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/gmsh-airplane.png" class="align-center" src="/images/gmsh-airplane.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://gmsh.info/"&gt;Gmsh&lt;/a&gt; has released a major version upgrade, which includes removing the
experimental Java API and introducing Julia bindings, although this package doesn't
do anything with them. The current version in the Debian archives is 3.0.6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This package is only available on Bionic (Ubuntu 18.04) due to its dependencies. I hadn't tried on
Cosmic (Ubuntu 18.10) since I worked on this in the beginning of October and it wasn't released yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="calculix-2-14"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Calculix 2.14&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/calculix-turbocharger.jpeg" class="align-center" src="/images/calculix-turbocharger.jpeg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.calculix.de/"&gt;CalculiX&lt;/a&gt; in Debian is currently several versions behind (2.11) so I got a request
to package this. However, CalculiX actually spans several packages, but calculix-ccx,
the solver, is the only one used by FreeCAD, so unlike the other packages, this one
is not quite ready for Debian until the other ones are done as well, since they are
separate source packages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This package is available on Bionic and Xenial (Ubuntu 16.04).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="translated-freecad-doc-packages"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Translated FreeCAD-Doc Packages&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the big areas for improvement in FreeCAD is the state of its documentation, and
I'm glad to announce that one big improvement is on its way. I have been working on
a standalone &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;freecad-doc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; package, since it was removed from the Debian archive for
being derived from pre-compiled binary files. This package involves using a local
synced copy of the FreeCAD Wiki text and images, and using the script that was used
to generate the aforementioned binary files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main improvement my package offers is support for the two most complete translations
of the FreeCAD wiki, French and Italian. This is accomplished by making &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;freecad-doc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;
a metapackage which depends on any one of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;freecad-doc-en&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;, &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;-it&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;, or &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;-fr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; being installed.
Then, the relevant files in &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;freecad-doc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; upon which &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;freecad&lt;/tt&gt; will call are in fact
managed symlinks to the appropriate translations. The symlinks are managed by the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://wiki.debian.org/DebianAlternatives"&gt;DebianAlternatives&lt;/a&gt; system (see update-alternatives(1).)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to switch between translations if more than one is installed, you can run
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;sudo &lt;span class="pre"&gt;update-alternatives&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;--config&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;freecad-doc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;. This will control the in-program help for FreeCAD,
so when you click the "What's this?" button, the resultant help page will be the translated version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, compiled PDFs of the FreeCAD help are provided for all three languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One result of the nature of this package is that it is quite large: each &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;freecad-doc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; translated package
weighs in about 300 MB so the combined size is about 1.2 GB, per Ubuntu distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, this package is only available on Bionic and Xenial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="pycollada-0-6-now-with-python-3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;PyCOLLADA 0.6, now with Python 3!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/collada.jpeg" class="align-center" src="/images/collada.jpeg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another package which is fairly out of date in Debian (version 0.4 present), I decided
to update it since &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/pycollada/pycollada"&gt;pycollada&lt;/a&gt; is a dependency of FreeCAD and I am intrigued by the possibilities
of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/COLLADA"&gt;COLLADA (COLLAborative Design Activity) format&lt;/a&gt;.
This allows for interchange with interactive 3D applications like Blender.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big news with this package is that Python 3 support is now available, so I updated the source packaging
to provide both Python 2 and 3 packages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again due to dependencies, it's only available on Cosmic and Bionic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="sponsors"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Sponsors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My work on Debian Science and FreeCAD is supported by my patrons at &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://patreon.com/kkremitzki"&gt;https://patreon.com/kkremitzki&lt;/a&gt;. Thank you all very much!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you appreciate my work as described in this post, any level of support is greatly appreciated, including moral support!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="social-media"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Social Media&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can follow me on Twitter at &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/thekurtwk"&gt;@thekurtwk&lt;/a&gt;. I'm also currently working on
a Twitch streaming setup, which I hope to have ready by the end of the year! I'll be trying out some live programming,
engineering, and Linux gaming. &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.twitch.tv/kkremitzki"&gt;You can find me at twitch.tv/kkremitzki&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>debian</category><guid>/blog/free-software-activities-in-october-2018/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Nov 2018 05:59:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Free Software Activities in September 2018</title><link>/blog/free-software-activities-in-september-2018/</link><dc:creator>Kurt Kremitzki</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hello all, unfortunately my update comes late again this month, although I have good reason! I just finished landing a job
as a scientific software developer. From the looks of it, I'll mostly be working on things from a systems engineering perspective,
but it'll be in the context of the scientific Python ecosystem as well as involving Qt. This is nice in that while I will have less
free time to spend on FreeCAD, it will almost certainly be of increasingly higher quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another interesting benefit of the job is that it will allow me to move back to Austin, which has the very well-equipped hackerspace
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://atxhs.org"&gt;ATX Hackerspace&lt;/a&gt;. I look forward to joining and having a chance to finally experiment with FreeCAD's CNC integrations,
and to have a great space to hack on hardware and software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, finally, to summarize what I've worked on in the month of September.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I created a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://forum.freecadweb.org/viewtopic.php?f=8&amp;amp;t=31046"&gt;thread on the FreeCAD forums&lt;/a&gt; to announce the revival of the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://launchpad.net/~freecad-community/+archive/ubuntu/ppa"&gt;FreeCAD Community Extras PPA&lt;/a&gt;. This will be used to host packages of interest
to the FreeCAD community, and things that need testing for possible future inclusion in FreeCAD. In retrospect, I should have used this PPA to get
testers for the packages I was working on during my last Google Summer of Code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;To this FreeCAD Community Extras PPA, I uploaded packages for:&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/aewallin/opencamlib"&gt;OpenCAMLIB&lt;/a&gt;, a C++ library with Python bindings for creating 3D toolpaths for CNC machines such as mills and lathes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/aewallin/openvoronoi"&gt;OpenVoronoi&lt;/a&gt;, another C++/Python library for 2D Voronoi diagrams for point and line-segment sites.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laughlin Research's standalone &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/LaughlinResearch/SMESH"&gt;SMESH&lt;/a&gt;, the Salome meshing framework.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/NGSolve/netgen"&gt;Netgen&lt;/a&gt;'s latest release, 6.2.1807, a 3D tetrahedral mesh generator.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/IfcOpenShell/IfcOpenShell"&gt;IfcOpenShell&lt;/a&gt;, an open source Python IFC library and geometry engine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/ifcquery/ifcplusplus"&gt;IfcPlusPlus&lt;/a&gt;, an open source C++ class model, reader, and writer for IFC files with simple Qt/OpenSceneGraph viewer application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have long been interested in having CAD database support, and I spent quite a bit of September working with my friend on research and initial work for this. From what we've found,
we can feasibly have a PostgreSQL extension similar to PostGIS, but for CAD: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/postcad"&gt;PostCAD&lt;/a&gt;. This would mainly involve a marriage between &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.opencascade.com/"&gt;OpenCASCADE&lt;/a&gt;, the C++ geometry and topology kernel of FreeCAD,
and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/jtv/libpqxx"&gt;libpqxx&lt;/a&gt;, the official C++ client library for PostgreSQL. The potential for such an extension would be huge, with all the power and features
of PostgreSQL with an understanding of CAD data and geometry. For example, FreeCAD could interface with this database, and have the database take care of things like editing locks
for models, permissions for readingn and writing of models, and so forth. Furthermore, by creating a database-level abstraction for CAD, that opens the way for web abstractions
for CAD, similar to GeoDjango's GIS extensions for Django. That work could one day pave the way for a web interface for FreeCAD.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, if you appreciate the work I do with FreeCAD, the Debian Science Team, and Open Engineering on Linux, any level of support would be appreciated
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://patreon.com/kkremitzki"&gt;on my Patreon!&lt;/a&gt; Currently this money helps offset server costs for some of the experimental FreeCAD community stuff.
I would like to continue to use it to offset my costs for FreeCAD development and equipment. If I can reach my current goal of $100/month, I'd like to
use it to purchase a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.pine64.org/?page_id=3707"&gt;Pinebook, a $99 ARM64 laptop&lt;/a&gt; which I could use for FreeCAD &amp;amp; Debian ARM development.
I'd really like FreeCAD to be usable (and not painfully slow) on ARM since its low-cost nature means it is highly available for educational institutions.
Maybe one day I'll even be able to afford milling/CNC equipment so I can see just how far FreeCAD integration can take us!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>debian</category><guid>/blog/free-software-activities-in-september-2018/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 14 Oct 2018 03:47:15 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Free Software Activities in August 2018</title><link>/blog/free-software-activities-in-august-2018/</link><dc:creator>Kurt Kremitzki</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hello all! After reading some of the nice activity logs published by members of the
Debian Project at &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://planet.debian.org"&gt;https://planet.debian.org&lt;/a&gt;, I've decided to publish my own version.
This will mostly be my work on FreeCAD and Debian, but will also include other points
of note from my many interests. I'll also include relevant activities for &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.patreon.com/kkremitzki"&gt;my supporters
on Patreon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As covered in my previous post, most of the first half of August was spent finishing
my Google Summer of Code project for FreeCAD, which largely turned into "packaging
for the Debian Science Team" since FreeCAD's dependency chain and options for
integration are so vast. However, the nature of the work is highly parallel.
For example, when packaging, most issues occur either almost immediately into the build,
or after the build has finished. This means that after an initial bit of packaging work
that allows a build to actually proceed, one then has to launch the build and wait
anywhere from a few minutes to a few hours to see the next issue arise. So, as a
result, I worked on &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; packages in parallel. A negative consequence of this was
that I somewhat overloaded my plate in terms of things I can handle, so in actuality
this meant I would work on a handful of packages on several machines at once, and then
once those issues were largely resolved I would move onto another handful, rather
than really juggling them all at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After finishing GSoC, I first turned my attention to two of the packages I had
worked on in parallel, python-fluids and python-ulmo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id1"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tracker.debian.org/pkg/python-fluids"&gt;python-fluids&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made a new upload for this package to correct several issues. Here's an excerpt from the changelog:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
* [1215102] Make python-fluids-doc Multi-Arch: foreign
* [eb610fd] Correct Vcs-* fields
* [62570cd] Updated to Standards-Version 4.2.0, no change required
* [29e96a7] Correct debian/watch
* [3e90d05] Add missing scipy dependency
* [cd776a2] Add lintian override for
  package-contains-documentation-outside-usr-share-doc
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The package still fails some reproducibility tests on i386 and could use a standards version bump, but other
than that, this package is almost completely clean now! It's quite satisfying cleaning up these packages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tracker.debian.org/pkg/python-ulmo"&gt;python-ulmo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made an upload for this package as well:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
* [7150daa] Correct Vcs-* fields
* [027b50b] Mark python-ulmo-doc as Multi-Arch: foreign
* [d72b6f6] Add patch to fix FutureWarning
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The package was failing its autopkgtests because Python was emitting a FutureWarning onto stderr.
This package is actually fully reproducible, and only needs a standards version bump to be fully clean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id3"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tracker.debian.org/pkg/gmsh"&gt;gmsh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On August 22nd, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://gmsh.info/"&gt;Gmsh 4.0.0 was released!&lt;/a&gt; The Java API was removed and a Julia one added.
This is a nice release because in
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=904946"&gt;Debian bug #904946&lt;/a&gt; it was found that the Gmsh package, after being updated to
be built against OCCT instead of OCE, actually no longer worked when used in FreeCAD, giving the error:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
Error   : Gmsh requires OpenCASCADE to import shape
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My hope was that by updating to the new Gmsh version, this problem would resolve itself. However, I ran into a few problems and had to postpone
finishing up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id4"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tracker.debian.org/pkg/netgen"&gt;netgen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On August 19th, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=906619"&gt;Debian bug #906619&lt;/a&gt; was reported against Netgen, which was
an occasion to look at the state of the package. I noticed that upstream had released version 6.2.1807 (versus the current .1804) but
it was not tagged in the Netgen repository, only as a submodule of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/ngsolve/ngsolve"&gt;Ngsolve repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On August 31st, I packaged the new version and resolved the bug
in &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://salsa.debian.org/science-team/netgen/merge_requests/9/commits"&gt;science-team/netgen PR #9&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="salome-smesh"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;salome-smesh&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although technically not August, on September 3rd I pushed the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://salsa.debian.org/kkremitzki-guest/salome-smesh"&gt;nearly finished package for a standalone salome-smesh on Salsa&lt;/a&gt;
which is fully functional except for an issue with the CMake config file. I submitted a pull request to support multi-arch for the package
but forgot to update the path in the CMake config file, so the variables therein have to be manually set, or the file edited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="cantera"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;cantera&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On August 24th, Cantera 2.4.0 was released:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
Cantera is an open-source suite of tools for problems involving chemical kinetics, thermodynamics, and transport processes.
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously there had been an issue with the build, where the packages would be made successfully, but attempting to &lt;cite&gt;import cantera&lt;/cite&gt; in
Python would error out, presumably due to the way an included copy of libfmt was handled during the build. However, the issue is no longer
present, so I now have a working Cantera 2.4.0 package! The only shortcoming is that I don't have working docs build yet, so this package
didn't make it in time for August.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id5"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tracker.debian.org/pkg/openfoam"&gt;openfoam&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously I had submitted a pull request for OpenFOAM 6 to the Debian Science Team, but spontaneously the package began to fail,
presumably due to some change in a dependency. I spent some time troubleshooting this issue but haven't found a resolution yet.
Here's a snippet of the build failure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
Allwmake src/Pstream
wmake dummy
wmakeLnIncludeAll: running wmakeLnInclude on dependent libraries:
    wmakeLnInclude: linking include files to /build/openfoam-6.20180805+dfsg1/src/OpenFOAM/lnInclude
    wmakeLnInclude: linking include files to /build/openfoam-6.20180805+dfsg1/src/OSspecific/POSIX/lnInclude
make[2]: Entering directory '/build/openfoam-6.20180805+dfsg1/src/Pstream/dummy'
wmakeLnInclude: linking include files to ./lnInclude
make[2]: Leaving directory '/build/openfoam-6.20180805+dfsg1/src/Pstream/dummy'
make[2]: Entering directory '/build/openfoam-6.20180805+dfsg1/src/Pstream/dummy'
Making dependency list for source file UOPwrite.C
realloc(): invalid next size
make[2]: *** Deleting file '/build/openfoam-6.20180805+dfsg1/platforms/linux64GccDPInt32Opt/src/Pstream/dummy/UOPwrite.C.dep'
Making dependency list for source file UIPread.C
realloc(): invalid next size
make[2]: *** Deleting file '/build/openfoam-6.20180805+dfsg1/platforms/linux64GccDPInt32Opt/src/Pstream/dummy/UIPread.C.dep'
Making dependency list for source file UPstream.C
realloc(): invalid next size
make[2]: *** Deleting file '/build/openfoam-6.20180805+dfsg1/platforms/linux64GccDPInt32Opt/src/Pstream/dummy/UPstream.C.dep'
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll have to continue investigating this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id6"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tracker.debian.org/pkg/pyside2"&gt;pyside2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I reported &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=906020"&gt;Debian bug #906020&lt;/a&gt; about missing Python 3 CMake config files,
which was fixed Aug 28th. I began investigating how this would Pivy builds, but got sidetracked by a problem with the &lt;cite&gt;med-fichier&lt;/cite&gt; package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id7"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tracker.debian.org/pkg/freecad"&gt;freecad&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ran into some build issues trying to update the package now that my Debian Unstable workstation is running Qt 5.11:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
error: invalid use of incomplete type class QAction
     QAction* action = new QAction(tr("Remove"), this);
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several instances of this throughout the codebase that can basically be fixed with by adding some &lt;cite&gt;#include&lt;/cite&gt; s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="projectchrono"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;projectchrono&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a bit of discussion about utilization of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.projectchrono.org/"&gt;Project Chrono&lt;/a&gt;, an open source multi-physics simulation engine,
in FreeCAD. One problem with pursuing this is that it isn't packaged at all for Debian, which is rather surprising! It seems like high-quality software.
I began looking at packaging it and it actually doesn't seem that bad. One of the main issues is actually the naming: it's really long! There's also a
bit of worry about naming collisions I'll have to look into. As of now, I have a working package except for the Python bindings. Enabling them results
in this failure in the build process:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
[ 53%] Building CXX object src/demos/irrlicht/CMakeFiles/demo_IRR_soilbin.dir/demo_IRR_soilbin.cpp.o
cd /build/project-chrono-3.0.0/obj-x86_64-linux-gnu/src/demos/irrlicht &amp;amp;&amp;amp; /usr/lib/ccache/c++  -DBP_USE_FIXEDPOINT_INT_32 -I/build/project-chrono-3.0.0/src -I/build/project-chrono-3.0.0/obj-x86_64-linux-gnu -I/build/project-chrono-3.0.0/src/chrono -I/build/project-chrono-3.0.0/src/chrono/collision/bullet -I/build/project-chrono-3.0.0/src/chrono/collision/gimpact -I/build/project-chrono-3.0.0/src/chrono/collision/convexdecomposition/HACD -I/usr/include/irrlicht  -g -O2 -fdebug-prefix-map=/build/project-chrono-3.0.0=. -fstack-protector-strong -Wformat -Werror=format-security -Wdate-time -D_FORTIFY_SOURCE=2 -pthread -fopenmp  -march=native -msse4.2 -mfpmath=sse  -march=native -mavx2  -march=native -mfma  -std=c++14 -pthread -fopenmp  -march=native -msse4.2 -mfpmath=sse  -march=native -mavx2  -march=native -mfma    -std=c++14 -pthread -fopenmp  -march=native -msse4.2 -mfpmath=sse  -march=native -mavx2  -march=native -mfma  -o CMakeFiles/demo_IRR_soilbin.dir/demo_IRR_soilbin.cpp.o -c /build/project-chrono-3.0.0/src/demos/irrlicht/demo_IRR_soilbin.cpp
/build/project-chrono-3.0.0/obj-x86_64-linux-gnu/swig/ChModuleCorePYTHON_wrap.cxx: In member function 'virtual void chrono::ChLogPython::Output(const char*, size_t)':
/build/project-chrono-3.0.0/obj-x86_64-linux-gnu/swig/ChModuleCorePYTHON_wrap.cxx:7610:23: error: format not a string literal and no format arguments [-Werror=format-security]
     PySys_WriteStdout(buffer);
                       ^~~~~~
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="opencamlib"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;opencamlib&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a problem with this package's doc depends, which I fixed at the end of August. However, it's still awaiting sponsorship to be uploaded
into the Debian archives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="med-fichier"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;med-fichier&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tracker.debian.org/pkg/med-fichier"&gt;med-fichier package&lt;/a&gt; in Debian currently is built with autotools but somewhat supports CMake builds, which
would be nice to switch to as it would provide CMake configuration files in libmedc-dev. I worked on updating the package, but currently building docs is broken,
and for some reason, the Fortran library is being statically linked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="planet-freecad"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Planet FreeCAD&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tracker.debian.org/pkg/planet-venus"&gt;planet-venus package&lt;/a&gt; in Debian is available for running your own RSS feed aggregation service.
I wanted to set up a planet.freecad.io to provide exactly that. However, the current version of the package is broken, and it only works in Debian 7, a.k.a. old-old-stable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent some time researching the state of the package, but it's fairly rough, and most importantly, upstream is far from active. I'd like to run the RSS service but
fixing the package seems like a tall order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="freecad-io"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;freecad.io&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We previously had two servers available to run some of the web services for the FreeCAD project, but sadly they rebooted but never came back online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm now paying for a VPS in Frankfurt using the money from &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://patreon.com/kkremitzki"&gt;my Patreon&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately, it's a bit resource-strained
from the FreeIPA server hogging things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="if-you-like-my-work-as-described-above-and-would-like-to-support-me-continuing-to-improve-the-state-of-open-engineering-on-linux-please-contribute-to-my-patreon"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;If you like my work as described above and would like to support me continuing to improve the state of open engineering on Linux, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://patreon.com/kkremitzki"&gt;please contribute to my Patreon!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>debian</category><guid>/blog/free-software-activities-in-august-2018/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 12 Sep 2018 10:20:13 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Google Summer of Code 2018 with FreeCAD</title><link>/blog/google-summer-of-code-2018-with-freecad/</link><dc:creator>Kurt Kremitzki</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hello all! This post is my final work product for GSoC 2018 for the FreeCAD project.
The main center for communication for FreeCAD is the forums, but we also coordinated things
through the #freecad channel on Freenode.
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://forum.freecadweb.org/viewtopic.php?f=8&amp;amp;t=28478"&gt;The main thread for my project was here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarize my project: FreeCAD is a complex application with an extensive dependency tree. The packaging
situation has always trailed the tip of development, which means users don't get to see the best FreeCAD
has to offer, and people trying to help new users have to deal with sometimes years-old bugs.
The goal was to improve the general ecosystem of the FreeCAD stack, and to cut down on technical debt to
make things easier moving forward. After some consideration it was decided to focus on Debian packaging
since that would be the most 'ecologically good'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I began with a rough knowledge of Debian packaging, but now feel competent
enough to want to take over the maintenance of Debian packaging for FreeCAD and several other packages
within the Debian Science Team, which will improve the free software engineering experience in Debian
as well as its derivatives such as Ubuntu and Linux Mint. In fact, I plan on trying to offically become
a Debian Maintainer and then Debian Developer. On the 4th of July during the middle of the project
I drove to Houston for a GPG keysigning, so the wheels are already in motion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post will summarize my work throughout the summer chronologically, mostly linking to emails in
the Debian Science mailing list, pull requests on Debian's Gitlab instance or Github, and to some repositories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More detailed information can be found at &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://salsa.debian.org/users/kkremitzki-guest"&gt;https://salsa.debian.org/users/kkremitzki-guest&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="coding-period-0-community-bonding-period-april-23-may-14"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Coding Period 0, Community Bonding Period (April 23 - May 14)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;May 8: RFS for python-fluids: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/05/msg00044.html"&gt;https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/05/msg00044.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Packaging this was part of learning more about Debian packaging, and because I'm a fan of the library
for its use in fluids engineering - part of overall ecosystem improvements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="coding-period-1-may-14-june-15"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Coding Period 1 (May 14 - June 15)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most of the first coding period was spent working on FreeCAD 0.17 packaging, as well as packaging Netgen 6.2.1804
and updating Gmsh to use OCCT, which I packaged prior to GSoC. I didn't finish them quite in time for submission
within the first coding period. I also spent time working on packaging PySide 2, which is a dependency for
FreeCAD's transition to Qt 5 &amp;amp; Python 3, but backed away after finding it was being worked on by others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;May 17: Netgen PR (Remove unnecessary backup files): &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/NGSolve/netgen/pull/15"&gt;https://github.com/NGSolve/netgen/pull/15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preparation work for packaging Netgen, which is used as a mesher by FreeCAD.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;May 25: Discussion of Netgen 6.2.1804 work: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/05/msg00101.html"&gt;https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/05/msg00101.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This was just me announcing that I was working on this so as to help not duplicate work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="coding-period-2-june-15-july-13"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Coding Period 2 (June 15 - July 13)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;June 19: Improvements to fluids after suggestions: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/06/msg00031.html"&gt;https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/06/msg00031.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;June 20: OpenFOAM 5 experimentation announced: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/06/msg00038.html"&gt;https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/06/msg00038.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This package is part of the FreeCAD ecosystem by way of its CFD (Computational Fluid Dynamics) workbench.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;June 21: RFS for netgen: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/06/msg00039.html"&gt;https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/06/msg00039.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Note: RFS = request for sponsorship, i.e. a submission of packaging work for Debian project members.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;June 21: RFS for gmsh: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/06/msg00040.html"&gt;https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/06/msg00040.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gmsh is another mesher used by FreeCAD.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;June 21: RFS for freecad: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/06/msg00041.html"&gt;https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/06/msg00041.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This was the packaging work for the FreeCAD 0.17 release.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;June 21: RFS for if97: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/06/msg00042.html"&gt;https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/06/msg00042.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This was another ecosystem project I worked on, a dependency for CoolProp, a powerful thermodynamics library.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;July 8: FreeCAD PR (Detect OCCT at new Debian location): &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/1545"&gt;https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/1545&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This was a housekeeping PR as a result of my Debian packaging work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;July 8: FreeCAD-Doc initial commit: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD-Doc/commits/master"&gt;https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD-Doc/commits/master&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The freecad-doc package was removed from Debian in 2016 for Debian Free Software Guidelines reasons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;July 11: Updated PPA to OCCT 7.3: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://launchpad.net/~freecad-maintainers/+archive/ubuntu/freecad-daily/+packages"&gt;https://launchpad.net/~freecad-maintainers/+archive/ubuntu/freecad-daily/+packages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This was a backport of Debian packaging work for OCCT 7.3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="coding-period-3-july-13-aug-14"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Coding Period 3 (July 13 - Aug 14)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;July 26: PR for horizon-eda (Support build against OCCT): &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/carrotIndustries/horizon/pull/181/files"&gt;https://github.com/carrotIndustries/horizon/pull/181/files&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As part of packaging OCCT, it is planned to phase out OCE (a community fork of OCCT which has stalled in development) and this
was more housekeeping work to update package dependencies from OCE-&amp;gt;OCCT.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;July 27: PR for deal.ii (Update dependencies &amp;amp; rules for liboce-&amp;gt;libocct transition): &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://salsa.debian.org/science-team/deal.ii/merge_requests/1"&gt;https://salsa.debian.org/science-team/deal.ii/merge_requests/1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Similar as above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;July 29: RFS for ulmo: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/07/msg00042.html"&gt;https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/07/msg00042.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This was an ecosystem packaging work, as this library was very useful for me in hydrology and for various agricultural engineering data needs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Aug 7: RFS for openfoam: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/08/msg00011.html"&gt;https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/08/msg00011.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My submission for OpenFOAM 5 was delayed by the release of OpenFOAM 6.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Aug 8: RFS for openvoronoi: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/08/msg00022.html"&gt;https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/08/msg00022.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This was a new dependency for FreeCAD's Path workbench which was relicensed so it could be directly integrated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Aug 8: RFS for opencamlib: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/08/msg00023.html"&gt;https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/08/msg00023.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Similar as above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Aug 10: PR for smesh (Fix GCC8 FTBFS): &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/LaughlinResearch/SMESH/pull/9"&gt;https://github.com/LaughlinResearch/SMESH/pull/9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part of packaging work for SMESH, a mesher used by FreeCAD which is included in the FreeCAD source (which is generally undesirable, and so packaging it would allow us to remove the included copy.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Aug 12: RFS for pivy: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/08/msg00041.html"&gt;https://lists.debian.org/debian-science/2018/08/msg00041.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PySide 2 was a dependency for pivy, so once it was packaged I was able to submit my work for pivy, which required upstreaming Python 3 support from FreeCAD's fork. This package was the last dependency for FreeCAD's Qt 5 &amp;amp; Python 3 transition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Aug 13: FreeCAD Qt 5/Python 3 builds provided in FreeCAD Daily PPA based on experimental (RFS submitted) packages: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://launchpad.net/~freecad-maintainers/+archive/ubuntu/freecad-daily/+packages"&gt;https://launchpad.net/~freecad-maintainers/+archive/ubuntu/freecad-daily/+packages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While bugs were indeed present, these next-generation FreeCAD builds still somewhat work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Aug 14: RFS for freecad-doc: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=906105"&gt;https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=906105&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Packaging for freecad-doc was delayed by my desire, by way of providing a multi-language supported package, to say thanks to the FreeCAD community translators who provided thorough French and Italian translations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Aug 14: SMESH repo: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://salsa.debian.org/kkremitzki-guest/salome-smesh"&gt;https://salsa.debian.org/kkremitzki-guest/salome-smesh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Packaging external SMESH is incomplete, as its current CMake instructions don't append the library version to the shared library, which will require patching.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Aug 14: CoolProp repo: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://salsa.debian.org/kkremitzki-guest/coolprop"&gt;https://salsa.debian.org/kkremitzki-guest/coolprop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Similar as above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that GSoC is done I am excited to continue working within the Debian Science Team. Besides an upcoming FreeCAD 0.18 release,
I have several packages I plan to make improvements to and to package for Debian, and ultimately to integrate into future
FreeCAD workbenches as part of my plan to make it the ultimate 3D engineering toolbox!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I must say thanks to the FreeCAD and Debian communities for working with me, and to my GSoC mentors and GSoC itself
for providing me this wonderful opportunity. May it continue providing valuable opportunities for others for many years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>/blog/google-summer-of-code-2018-with-freecad/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2018 08:51:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Looking Back on 2017</title><link>/blog/looking-back-on-2017/</link><dc:creator>Kurt Kremitzki</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;2017 has been an incredible year for me with lots of opportunities, but many
challenges as well. In the spring, I got a (lab) teaching opportunity for a
50-student Measurement &amp;amp; Control of Biological Systems course, culminating in
17 teams making maze-solving autonomous robots. There's a higher level of
mastery to be attained by teaching others, and in that regard, it was an
incredible experience. Teaching, however, is well outside my comfort zone, and
in that regard it had some difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the summer, I was able to work on a Google Summer of Code project/pseudo-internship.
Working in a mix of Python and C++ was again an interesting challenge since
I'm much more familiar with the former than the latter, and even my experience
with other languages lies on the Python side of the interpreted/compiled,
dynamic/static typing divide. Still, it was an invaluable experience since C++
rules the domain of finite element analysis and computational fluid dynamics,
which I want to explore further. Particularly, FreeCAD is the perfect vehicle for
engineering computer modeling, so I have high hopes for my future with the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the summer, I passed the exam for the Linux Foundation Certified
System Administrator. This was an opportunity provided by a scholarship given
in part because of my work using Python to analyze the efficiency of backyard
irrigation systems in the Yucatn back in early 2016, so it was great to finally
see the culmination of that work. As a little celebration project, I decided to
begin running my own Linux mail server, which has been a great success. There
were a few hiccups with blacklists on Yahoo and Outlook, but I was ultimately
able to get it working with all the major email providers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also embarked on a project I've been wanting to do for a long time: running
my own Linux router. I found a great series of tutorials on setting up such a
router using Ubuntu and the Pine64 board, and have had excellent results since.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also been spending time here and there researching a really promising
project, FreeIPA. It's a sort of competitor to Active Directory in the identity
management space, mostly made up of a combination of an LDAP, Kerberos, and
certificate server. I'm running a sort of pseudo-small business in my home
network using my FreeIPA server as a centralized authentication, authorization,
and identity server, and it's been a great experience so far; I hope to apply it
in reality with the FreeCAD project one day. Look out for future posts on the
topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the fall, I began my final year at Texas A&amp;amp;M. My capstone project and team
was assigned. Our project involves analyzing the flood resiliency of the Houston
area and proposing an ecological engineering design to improve that resiliency and
mitigate the effects of future extreme flood events such as was seen during
Hurricane Harvey. We are using an open-source toolchain involving PostGIS, Python,
and QGIS, and the project is really quite exciting since our analysis could be applied
to other coastal cities and regions facing extreme weather events in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Altogether, it's been a great year, but I foresee 2018 being even better. If
you're reading this, I want to wish you a happy new year with hope for the same!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>/blog/looking-back-on-2017/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2017 07:30:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>GSoC Week 12: Final Work Product</title><link>/blog/gsoc-week-12-final-work-product/</link><dc:creator>Kurt Kremitzki</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Well, it's time to finally wrap up the summer!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's been a really great and rewarding opportunity, so I first want to thank everyone at Google and beyond who helped put GSoC together,
as well as my mentor Stefan Trger for providing feedback and guidance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was able to work with code that ranged almost the entire stack of FreeCAD dependencies: from low-level OpenCASCADE code involving
quaternions &amp;amp; transformations, geometry &amp;amp; topology; to the scene graph library Coin3D we have to thank for our pretty screenshots;
the connection between C++ and Python code, which I have a feeling will be useful later in my engineering career; and all the way up to the
Qt GUI in both C++ as well as its Python interface PySide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, I feel very prepared to continue working with the FreeCAD project and look forward to doing so. I really think it's a great
program and hope to use it for many years in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So again, my thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main goal of the project was to get test coverage of the Part Design Workbench, and to explore it to find showstopping bugs. The only
remaining one involves a crash in ShapeBinder, discussed at &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://freecadweb.org/tracker/view.php?id=2517"&gt;https://freecadweb.org/tracker/view.php?id=2517&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I fixed quite a few bugs and I think the general experience with the workbench is better.
Test coverage is there for all the tools, and I'd say the workbench is ready for the public, so now the major work is to release FreeCAD 0.17,
the biggest FreeCAD release ever, with its new Part Design (no longer "NEXT") Workbench.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My other goal of improvements to Boolean Operation was made unnecessary by someone else's PR in May.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last goal, improvements to the Attachment Editor, ended up being a little too big for this GSoC, and could even possibly serve
as a good GSoC project for next summer, although whoever does it had better be fairly artistic at making explanatory yet small icons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, I'd say the summer was a success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Altogether, my code contribution can be summarized with 7 PRs and one experimental branch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PR's:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/816"&gt;https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/816&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/829"&gt;https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/829&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/848"&gt;https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/848&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/869"&gt;https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/869&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/899"&gt;https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/899&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/920"&gt;https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/920&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/957"&gt;https://github.com/FreeCAD/FreeCAD/pull/957&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experimental Attachment Editor/PartDesign Datum Tools branch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/kkremitzki/freecad/tree/pdn_datum_tools"&gt;https://github.com/kkremitzki/freecad/tree/pdn_datum_tools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's my summary posts, summarized:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/blog/gsoc-week-1-recap/"&gt;/blog/gsoc-week-1-recap/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/blog/gsoc-week-2-recap/"&gt;/blog/gsoc-week-2-recap/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/blog/gsoc-week-3-recap/"&gt;/blog/gsoc-week-3-recap/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/blog/gsoc-week-4-recap/"&gt;/blog/gsoc-week-4-recap/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/blog/gsoc-week-5-recap/"&gt;/blog/gsoc-week-5-recap/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/blog/gsoc-week-6-recap/"&gt;/blog/gsoc-week-6-recap/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/blog/gsoc-week-7-recap/"&gt;/blog/gsoc-week-7-recap/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/blog/gsoc-week-8-recap/"&gt;/blog/gsoc-week-8-recap/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/blog/gsoc-week-9-recap/"&gt;/blog/gsoc-week-9-recap/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/blog/gsoc-week-10-recap/"&gt;/blog/gsoc-week-10-recap/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/blog/gsoc-week-11-recap/"&gt;/blog/gsoc-week-11-recap/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>/blog/gsoc-week-12-final-work-product/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 27 Aug 2017 17:50:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>GSoC Week 11 Recap</title><link>/blog/gsoc-week-11-recap/</link><dc:creator>Kurt Kremitzki</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, it looks like solid, usable improvements to the Attachment Editor are unlikely to be ready for a PR
by the end of my GSoC, although I will publish my experimental branch which uses Python for the datum tools and uses the Python-based
Attachment Editor I mentioned previously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, as a consolation I did finalize some additional tests for PartDesign Hole, so my goal of functional coverage of the PartDesign tools
succeeded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I think with this foray into GUI code, I've hit nearly the full stack of libraries used in FreeCAD this summer. It feels pretty nice, because
I feel prepared to tackle whatever problem I want to in the FreeCAD project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>/blog/gsoc-week-11-recap/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 22 Aug 2017 12:31:55 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>GSoC Week 10 Recap</title><link>/blog/gsoc-week-10-recap/</link><dc:creator>Kurt Kremitzki</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final portion of GSoC for me will be dedicated to working on improvements to the Attachment Editor, and this post will essentially be my design
for what those improvements will look like. The Attachment Editor is available in the Part Workbench through Python. One can for example create a simple
Part Cube, select it, then click Part -&amp;gt; Attachment. It also is used when creating datum geometry in Part Design, or when creating a primitive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few screenshots:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure align-center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="command palette" src="/images/gsoc-10-1.png"&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 1. The Python-based Attachment Editor in the Part workbench.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure align-center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="command palette" src="/images/gsoc-10-2.png"&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 2. Creating a Datum Plane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating datum geometry is a key part of the Part Design process, so it's helpful for it to be very easy and intuitive. The current
Attachment Mode information especially can be quite overwhelming to a beginner, however. Especially considering how improvements
to the Attachment Editor could be reused in a future Assembly Workbench, it was decided to look into improving these tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first, most obvious improvement here would be inactivating the "Extra placement" section when inactive. This could
possibly be accomplished by making a separate collapsible section which automatically hides when there is no attachment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second, and tougher improvement, involves reworking the current the four attachment selections and the attachment mode.
Reference names probably don't need to be more than 3/4ths the width of the page. The methods for selecting references via
an activation button, and deleting via clearing out the text are not user-friendly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The four-reference list here would ideally be replaced with an icon-based grid, which starts out empty. Each selection's icon would
be based on its type, e.g. Vertex, Edge, Face, Curve, etc., where available, and a generic icon for unrecognized types. The selection's name
could be displayed in a shortened form, e.g. "MyLongShapeNameIs...". This approach could be extended for future Assembly use by adding a scrollbar
on the icons, allowing for several rows of attachment references, 4 at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tool could be very user-friendly, as invalid reference icons can be highlighted red, and when the attachment is complete, the reference set's icons
can be highlighted green. Ghosted icons can be displayed as needed for a selected Attachment Mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A similar approach for Attachment Mode could be used. Using a 4-icon row with a scrollbar, attachment modes can be explained with a short label and
an icon, where feasible; hopefully the large size will allow for expressive icons. When a mode is moused over or selected, the remaining references required
can be displayed in the reference selection area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Altogether, (i) splitting out the placement and toggling when it has no effect (i.e. there is no attachment) and (ii) reworking Reference Selection and Attachment Mode
dialogs to use unified icon list GUI code, as well as (iii) making the icon set to explain the attachment concepts to users, comprise the components of this
"Attachment Editor Improvement" project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>/blog/gsoc-week-10-recap/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 20 Aug 2017 12:22:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>GSoC Week 9 Recap</title><link>/blog/gsoc-week-9-recap/</link><dc:creator>Kurt Kremitzki</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I celebrated my birthday in south Texas last week! I was about 3 miles from the future SpaceX launch facility opening in 2018.
It'll be great to possibly see launches to Mars from there in the next few years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mostly spent this week working on the bugs I mentioned last week. I wanted to try to make a dent in the outstanding bugs I've found.
Unfortunately, my lack of C++ background (compared to Python) really hampered this; it's a little bit like trying to run before you walk.
In the end, I only fixed the Revolution bug(s). In the case where a revolution is attempted on the same plane as the sketch, resulting in e.g. a flat disc,
the issue was that the code was checking the angle between the sketch's normal and the revolution plane's normal, looking for a 0 angle. However,
it was failing to fail in the case of a 180 angle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also added a simple convenience check for all tools in Part Design: if you open a document with only one body and try to click a PDN tool's button,
the single body will be auto-activated instead of popping up a warning. If there are no bodies or more than one, the warning still occurs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>/blog/gsoc-week-9-recap/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2017 02:18:04 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>