<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Biosystems Engineering Blog (Posts about freecad)</title><link>https://kkrem.it/zki/</link><description></description><atom:link type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" href="/blog/tags/freecad.xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 06 May 2017 09:08:55 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>My FreeCAD project was accepted into Google Summer of Code!</title><link>/blog/my-freecad-project-was-accepted-into-google-summer-of-code/</link><dc:creator>Kurt Kremitzki</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's been almost a year since my last post, which just so happened to be about FreeCAD
as well. It's been a busy year: I've been studying machine design, robotics; partial differential
equations in general, and heat and mass transfer in particular. I've also been studying the source
code of FreeCAD while honing my sysadmin skills by helping maintain project infrastructure.
My hard work has paid off, and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/projects/#5752969237626880"&gt;my Google Summer of Code project proposal &lt;/a&gt;
was accepted! I'm going to be working on improving the parametric part design workbench and writing
test code to make the module more robust for future development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, I've decided to publish my daily log here. I'll be posting weekly summaries once the
coding period begins on May 30, as well as more in-depth ad hoc blogging on interesting developments over the summer.
My goal is to both document my project and to produce a useful reference for other developers wanting to get started
contributing to FreeCAD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of May is part of the Community Bonding Period, and so I'll ramp up to full speed with an introductory series
of posts. Here are a few rough-draft titles to highlight my planned topics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/distcc/distcc"&gt;Neovim&lt;/a&gt; as an IDE:&lt;ol class="arabic"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Building a base, or practically pluginless&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What makes an IDE? An overview of features&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unix as an IDE, or knowing your tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neovim with Python 2 and 3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neovim with C++&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Building the project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Distributed compilation with &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/distcc/distcc"&gt;distcc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speaking source code: how to fix your first FreeCAD bug&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contributing to open source communities (and FreeCAD in particular)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>freecad</category><guid>/blog/my-freecad-project-was-accepted-into-google-summer-of-code/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 06 May 2017 07:41:23 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>